ARI DECTER-FRAIN

PhD Student - Cornell Policy Analysis and Management

■ agd75@cornell.edu — 🎓 aridecterfrain.com — 🗘 aridf — in aridecterfrain — 🛩 adecterfrain

SUMMARY

I am a versatile and collaborative problem-solver. I am fulfilled by rigorous work that promotes social good. I can contribute to any team by drawing on practical experience in leadership and product development, combined with broad knowledge of the social sciences and an ever-growing toolkit of computational social science methods.

EDUCATION

Cornell University

08/2019 - Present Ithaca, NY, USA

PhD Policy Analysis and Management (PAM)

• Relevant Coursework: Bayesian Data Analysis; Machine Learning for Data Science; Spatial Demography; Econometrics; Microeconomics; OOP and Data Structures

• Teaching Assistantships: Statistics for Policy Analysis and Management Majors

London School of Economics and Political Science

2016 - 2017

MSc Inequalities and Social Science (Distinction)

London, UK

- Dissertation: Patterns of Precarious Employment Among Migrants to the United Kingdom
- Relevant Coursework: Causal Inference from Observational Data; Welfare Analysis and Measurement; The Politics of Inequality and Redistribution; Multidisciplinary Approaches to Inequality

University of Winnipeg

2012 - 2016

Bachelor of Arts (Honors) Psychology (GPA 4.44/4.50)

Winnipeg, MB, CA

WORK EXPERIENCE

Data Science for Social Good Fellow

06/2020 - 08/2020 Seattle, WA, US

University of Washington eScience Institute

• Developed eiCompare 3.0, an R package for quantifying minority vote dilution in US elections; made package available on github and CRAN for open-sourced distribution.

- Refactored nearly all code from previous version, incorporated diagnostics for Bayesian MCMC algorithms, added parallel processing; software became more efficient, accurate, and transparent.
- Incorporated feedback from stakeholders at the ACLU, National Democratic Redistricting Committee, and the UCLA Voting Rights Project; led to immediate adoption by these organizations.

Product Manager

08/2018 - 05/2019

Multi Health Systems (MHS) - Technology R&D

Toronto, ON, CA

- Assumed product ownership of a workplace mental health screening assessment, championed the social and business importance of worker well-being; achieved a five-fold increase in unit sales.
- Supervised a team of two software developers and a data scientist to support distributors' API integrations; developed, tested, and released new features.
- Conducted a top-down revision of the product's business model and profitability; streamlined company product portfolio and improved future profitability.

11/2017 - 08/2018 Toronto, ON, CA

Multi Health Systems (MHS) - Innovation Hub

- Designed and implemented a minimum viable product for an automated custom assessment-builder application; instigated company transition from a per-unit to a subscription revenue model.
- Built an R-based psychological assessment scoring and reporting system; first company use of dynamic reporting in a product, first use of R as a production-level coding language.
- Developed an algorithm to automatically shorten assessment products; reduced length of an emotional intelligence test by 80 percent while maintaining integrity of key results.

Laboratory Manager / Research Assistant

08/2013 - 04/2016

University of Winnipeg - Moral Psychology Lab

Winnipeg, MB, CA

- Developed leadership and collaboration skills while supervising research assistants and thesis students conducting research in moral and political psychology.
- Designed, conducted, analysed and reported on 10+ research projects, including linguistic analyses using LIWC, online and lab experiments, meta-analyses, and literature reviews.

Researcher

09/2013 - 04/2016

Public Interest Law Centre of Manitoba (PILC)

Winnipeg, MB, CA

• Developed research and strategic analysis skills while writing and presenting briefings to senior lawyers as part of the 2014 Needs For and Alternatives To review of Manitoba Hydros preferred hydroelectric development plan.

PUBLICATIONS AND PRESENTATIONS

Decter-Frain, A., Frimer, J.A. (2017). Agentic and communal rhetoric in the quest for political popularity. Talk presented at the European Association of Social Psychology (EASP) conference.

Decter-Frain, A., Vanstone, R., Frimer, J. A. (2017). Why and how do moralistic groups create heroes? In Allison, S. T., Goethals, G. R., Kramer, R. M. (Eds.). Handbook of heroism and heroic leadership. New York: Routledge.

Decter-Frain, A., Frimer, J.A. (2016). Impressive words: Linguistic predictors of public approval of U.S. Congress. Frontiers in Psychology: Personality and Social Psychology. doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2016.00240

TECHNICAL SKILLS

R, Python for data; HTML, CSS for web; PostgreSQL for databases Coding Software Rstudio, Jupyter Notebooks, LaTeX, pg Admin 4, Microsoft Office, SPSS

ADDITIONAL ACTIVITIES

08/20 - Present Treasurer Ithaca, NY

Graduate Students in Policy Analysis and Management

11/16 - 04/17

Consulting Team Leader 180 Degrees Consulting

London, UK

Oxford Spring School of Advanced Research Methods Oxford Department of Politics and International Relations

04/17 Oxford, UK

Board Member and Volunteer

09/12 - 05/2017 Winnipeg, MB, Canada

Sholem Aleichem Community